<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to the reflections on the five Jesuits speeches, or, General rules of Christian charity together with the speech of Henry IV, King of France, in behalf of the Jesuits.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13413764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13413764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 782:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to the reflections on the five Jesuits speeches, or, General rules of Christian charity together with the speech of Henry IV, King of France, in behalf of the Jesuits.</title>
                  <author>Henry IV, King of France, 1553-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="political_tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99450:1"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE REFLECTIONS on the Five JESUITS <hi>SPEECHES.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">OR, General Rules of CHRISTIAN CHARITY.</head>
            <head type="sub">TOGETHER WITH <hi>The Speech of</hi> HENRY IV. <hi>King of</hi> France <hi>in behalf of the</hi> Jeſuits.</head>
            <p>FOr purpoſes beſt known to the Divine Wiſdom, God has been pleaſed to ſuffer amongſt men, ſome who never had inclination to goodneſs, generoſity, or any the leaſt moral virtue: Such true Children of him who was a Lyer from the beginning, cannot indure any other man ſhould be eſteem'd pious, juſt, or true; of ſuch our Bleſſed Saviour ſpeaks <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.18. Theſe Diabolical natures combat Religion as their moſt mortal Enemy, in what ſhape ſoever they meet it: If it appear in ſevere mortified Devotion, then it is called by them madneſs, as of St. <hi>John Baptiſt, Behold a man that has a Devil;</hi> If it comes dreſt in the charming ſhape of Love and Sociable Converſation: Then (as the Bleſſed Jeſus) beheld a Drunkard and a Wine Bibber, a friend of Publicans and ſinners; Such children of Perdition, full of Envy, Malice, and all ungodlineſs, are ever buſie and taking more pains to ſerve the kingdom of darkneſs, and compleating their full meaſure of wickedneſs, then the beſt of Saints do to arrive at thoſe bleſſed Manſions prepared by their loving Redeemer in the Kingdom of the God of Love: Of this ſort of Spirit muſt he certainly be, who was Author of the Preamble and Poſtſcript Printed with the Jeſuites Speeches: For were it likely that men ſhould be ſo Infatuated by the Principles of any Religion, as to die with expectation of reward from him they call the God of Truth, when they invok'd him with their laſt breath as witneſs to a Lye, could it be poſſible, I ſay, that men ſhould arrive at ſuch madneſs. Yet ought poor limitted and undiſcerning men leave them to the Judgment of the Great, Wiſe, Juſt &amp; All ſeeing God to puniſh them as they deſerve: But nothing is more certain than this Truth, that the God of Truth hates falſehood above all things; and therefore when provok'd both by that, and the utmoſt contempt of his Divine Majeſty, by being invok'd to be a witneſs to a Lye, he will above all Crimes puniſh ſuch contempts with his utmoſt vengeance: And is it poſſible, but that all men of all Religions, who believe at all the Immortality of the Soul, ſhould alſo believe this Truth as certainly as they muſt believe there is a Divinity, which gave their Souls that immortality. Yet dares this uncharitable Author, as if he were the great ſearcher of hearts, accuſe five perſons, pretending (as he ſays,) to Dignified Orders of Religion and Sanctity, together with the perfections of Noble Learning (which uſually betters men) to break through all the Impalements of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Morality, and with a terrible Lye to take their ultimate farewells, meerly for the vanity of Impoſing a belief of Martyrdom, and to inſinuate their Hereſie into the Credulous and unſtable: Oh! moſt ridiculous concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unlikely indeed to bear ſo great ſway with the living as the laſt words would do of the moſt Notorious Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, much leſs theirs who by a continued ſeries of Good Life and Modeſt Behaviour had ſpent their time, (as they thought,) in their ſervice of God, living ſome of them to a great Age, without being Accuſed of any Crime againſt Humane Society, until this the worſt of Crimes which was Sworn againſt them; but that ſingle one of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning the Murther of Gods Vicegerent their Anointed King, if true, was enough to make black a continued life of virtue, longer then <hi>Methuſalem;</hi> but they with their laſt breaths deny their guilt, and others upon the Bible ſwear it, theſe are but four, and they were but five, thoſe were perſons who had Dedicated themſelves wholly to the Service of God in the way they [at leaſt] believed true; three of theſe are men by their own Confeſſions guilty of many Foul and Notorious Crimes, not yet giving the leaſt Teſtimony to the World of their Converſions by a good life, all of them of Indigent and Deſperate Fortunes, which they have well amended by their pretended Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries; which true or falſe, it concerns them as to their well being here to make good; the others can have no benefit by their Atteſtation, (but if falſe) the Eternal Damnation of their Souls; a bribe no man would be found of. Now if this be ſeriouſly conſidered on both ſides, will it not be enough to ſway with the moſt Partial Standers by, at leaſt to ſuſpend his Opinion of the Truth until it ſhall be revealed either in this World, or the next by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, to whom they have ſides on both appealed, and who alone ſees Truth through all Diſguiſes.</p>
            <p>But not to ſuffer all the dirt to ſtick, the malicious Pen of this Author has thrown on their (at worſt but doubtful) Memories, we will ſlightly conſider the ſtrength of his Arguments, avoiding all offences to the Magiſtrate and the Laws we live under, by whom ſuppoſing this (ſcarce probable) Evidence againſt them true, they were moſt unjuſtly Condemned.</p>
            <p>His Preamble &amp; firſt Paragraph of his Poſtſcript, tends only to perſwade us that theſe 5 dying men did hope by their damnable Lyes to eſcape Purgatory and leave it on their Left Hand, and at once skip from the Cart to <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, mount directly up to Heaven; which no man in his right Wits can believe, except their Accuſers will ſwear they told them ſo, or that he would produce ſome Authority from Popiſh Doctors, that ſhould not only allow Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation lawful, but dying in a Lye Meritorious: For as for his calling them in the cloſe of that Paragraph <hi>Ipſo functo</hi> Rebels and Malefactors when they firſt Arrived, that can be no proof againſt them, ſince the ſame Argument holds againſt Chriſtianity it ſelf propagated by the Apoſtles and their followers contrary to the Laws of Nations then in force: And to which all perſons pretending to make Converts may readily reply in the words of the Apoſtle forbid by the Jews to preach any more in the name of Jeſus, <hi>Whether it be better to obey God or man, judge ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not undertake to vindicate the Religion theſe men Died in, much leſs the Opinions or Extravagancies of ſome Doctors of it, the Laws forbidding the one, and the Romiſh Church it ſelf the other; I will therefore only ſay it is no more juſt to tax the whole Society with the Heterodox Opinion of two or three men, then it would be to accuſe Proteſtant Religion with King-killing Principles, from the practices of ſome called ſo in the Murther of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt; and from the multitude of Sermons and other Diſcourſes Printed in Commendation and Vindication of that deteſtable villanie: But becauſe our Author refers much to the Oration made to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> I will only by way of Reply, inſert that Great Kings Anſwer to it, mention'd by Mr. <hi>Gaven,</hi> which was in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99450:2"/>
                        <head>The Speech of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. King of <hi>France</hi> in behalf of the Jeſuits.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> THe care you ſhew of me and my Kingdom is grateful to me; albeit you ſeem not to have throughly weighed the things you demand, nor are you, as yet, ſo well acquainted with my thoughts, as I am with yours.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> You deem the weal of my Kingdom to conſiſt in the propoſition you have made; and you tell me it is a matter that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be moſt carefully deliberated. And I tell you, you have ſaid nothing which I have not moſt carefully weighed, and moſt diligently examined by my ſelf theſe Eight or Nine Years.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3.</hi> You take your ſelves for men of great underſtanding and experience in the Common wealth. But believe me, I know as well as You all that hath been in Controverſy in this matter.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4.</hi> Firſt of all you object to the Fathers of the Society, the Aſſembly of <hi>Poiſſy;</hi> 
                           <note n="*" place="margin">The Clergy held an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly at <hi>Poiſſy anno</hi> 1561. in which the Society was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of, and admitted though not fully.</note> but without cauſe. For if there had been at that place others like many of them, the Catholick Cauſe would have had a more happy ſucceſs. Therefore that which you turn to their Diſpraiſe, any juſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire will attribute to their Virtue. But that which I moſt wonder at your Judgments for, is, that ſo prepoſterouſly you condemn the Society of Ambition, whereas the Fathers of the Society with a conſtant Submiſſion, have ever refuſed all Honour and Preferment, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Political: And which is more, they bind themſelves by Vow not only not to aſpire to Honours, but even to refuſe the ſame when they are freely offered unto them. Conſider their whole courſe of life, and you ſhall find that all their Ambition is to labour for to help all, and that without any pretence of Intereſt or Gain. They value not the expences of their own pains, ſo they may profit many.</p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <hi>5.</hi> But you call to queſtion the very name of the Society of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and for that you tax them. But ſee with what reaſon, For if they muſt be blamed for that holy name, what ſhall we ſay for thoſe Religious perſons who take their name from the moſt bleſſed Trinity? And your Daughters here at <hi>Paris;</hi> what will you think of them that call themſelves <hi>Daughters of God?</hi> Finally how will you cenſure my Knights, who are called of the Holy Ghoſt? Truly I do not more diſlike them that take their name from Chriſt, then any other.</p>
                        <p n="6">
                           <hi>6.</hi> You object that the Divines of <hi>Sorbon</hi> condemned the Jeſuites. I do not deny it. But they condemned them being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, unknown, and unheard. For this I call to witneſs, thoſe very Divines themſelves, who now admit them, whom their Predeceſſors baniſhed, and honour them whom they contemned; nay they praiſe now and extoll thoſe that were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſtick not to take them for their Directors, and Maſters, in all kind of Learning.</p>
                        <p n="7">
                           <hi>7.</hi> You tell me Jeſuits have hitherto remained in <hi>France</hi> only by connivance. Here I acknowledge, and reverence the Divine Providence, that hath reſerved this Honour for me, not yet Atchieved by others, that I ſhould eſtabliſh in this Realm the Society of Jeſus, which hitherto hath had no ſettled abode in <hi>France.</hi> My Predeceſſors have received the Society, I will Patronize and preſerve them.</p>
                        <p n="8">
                           <hi>8.</hi> Peradventure you will turn to the Jeſuites diſcredit, that for which you ought to praiſe and honour them: The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Paris</hi> earneſtly and openly oppoſed them. And what, I pray, was the cauſe of this oppoſition? All was, that the Fathers did not only equal others in Learning and Induſtry, but alſo went far beyond them. A clear Teſtimony of this is the great number of Youth that frequented the Fathers Schools, where (together with Learning) they Learnt vertue. But to ſtop this oppoſition, I will make a Decree that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities of <hi>Paris</hi> ſhall no more oppoſe them. And this you will be glad of.</p>
                        <p n="9">
                           <hi>9.</hi> But you will tell me, that the ableſt of your Parliament got not their Learning of the Jeſuites, This I will not much gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay. For the ableſt of you, as they excel in Learning ſo they exceed in years. Theſe got their Learning in Forreign Nations, before the Society ſet foot in <hi>France.</hi> Others did not ſo, and ſo I am certain they think and ſpeak otherwiſe. And what need they ſpeak? the matter it ſelf ſpeaks. We our ſelves ſaw how at the departure of the Society out of <hi>France,</hi> all the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſeemed to depart. Our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity was deſert and mourned: Thoſe came ſeldom at it, who before in great numbers fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented the Fathers. Yea many departed the Realm, and forſook their Country to ſtudy in the Societies Schools; nor could your Decrees or Threats ſtop them.</p>
                        <p n="10">
                           <hi>10.</hi> You ſay the Fathers joyned themſelves to the League, that is not to be imputed to their fault, but to the iniquity of the times. But this I perſwade my ſelf, upon the aſſurance I have of the Integrity of their Conſciences, that they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch towards me, as it behoveth them, who mindful of benefits, deſire to ſhew themſelves moſt grateful.</p>
                        <p n="11">
                           <hi>11.</hi> Now ſome of you impoſe on the Fathers a new Crime, and peradventure as yet unheard of, ſaying, that they draw to their Order young men of the moſt forwardneſs and beſt diſpoſitions. An unpardonable Crime; yet I praiſe them and eſteem them particularly for this that you condemn. Do not we, though in a different matter, do the ſelf ſame? A Captain that is to raiſe Souldiers, does he not cull out the choiceſt, and leave the meaneſt and leſt hopeful? In your Parliament, when you chooſe a new Court, or fill up an old, do you prefer the unlearnedſt, and leaſt apt for buſineſs? If the Jeſuites put <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Maſters in their Schools, or in their Churches ignorant Preachers, would you not with reaſon blame them? What of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is it that the Jeſuits ſhould provide the fitteſt they can, both for Church and Schools.</p>
                        <p n="12">
                           <hi>12.</hi> That ſlander which concerns the Jeſuits Treaſure, is as falſe as common. Go viſit all the Colledges in <hi>France,</hi> ſearch all their Treaſures, ſum all together, and you will ſcarce find twelve, or at moſt fifteen thouſand Crowns. I know well how poor and ſl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nder furniture and Proviſion was both at <hi>Lyons</hi> and <hi>Bourges.</hi> Nevertheleſs <hi>30</hi> or <hi>40</hi> perſons were to be fed in each of theſe Colledges; whereas their yearly Revenues was ſcarcely ſufficient for eight Maſters.</p>
                        <p n="13">
                           <hi>13</hi> The Vow of Obedience with which they tye themſelves to the Pope doth not oblige them to be more faithful to externes, then to us Neither is there in that Vow any thing contrary to the Oath which they will ſwear unto me. They will attempt nothing (I am ſure) againſt their Prince. That Vow to the Pope, bindeth them to go to Barbarous and Savage Nations that they may reduce them to the Catholick Church. The whole World teſtifieth that the remoteſt Regions of the <hi>Indies,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with infinite Hereticks, have been by their pains and Learned endeavours brought to Chriſts fold. I remember I have often ſaid, that if the labour of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fathers be ſo profitable for <hi>Spain,</hi> why ſhould not <hi>France</hi> with reaſon expect the ſame? Is that Kingdom more fortunate and flouriſhing then this? <hi>Spain</hi> is loved by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and why ſhould the <hi>French</hi> hate their Native Soil?</p>
                        <p n="14">
                           <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99450:2"/>
                           <hi>14.</hi> But as you are wont to ſay, theſe men ſeek to be admitted into Provinces and Kingdoms what way ſoever they can. Pray you is this an offence? 'Tis the cuſtome of all that follow the inſtinct of nature. I my ſelf, by what means I could, ſought to get my Crown. Howſoever we cannot admire the Fathers conſtant patience whereby they go through ſo great and hard matters, and bear ſo many and ſo heavy Croſſes.</p>
                        <p n="15">
                           <hi>15.</hi> Neither do I Eſteem them the worſe, for that they be ſo obſervant of their Rules and Conſtitutions. This is that whereby the Society doth increaſe, flouriſh and better it ſelf every day more and more. For this reaſon I thought not good to change any of their Conſtitutions or Rules, though I have made ſome change in others, which was not approved of all. But that's no matter.</p>
                        <p n="16">
                           <hi>16.</hi> The Fathers of the Society hath many back friends, among ſome that ſeem Holy and Religious perſons, who ſpeak ill of them. This no wiſe man will wonder at. Our Age is not come to that ſanctity, that Ignorance ſhould ceaſe to hate Learning, or corruption of manners leave to envy integrity of life. It was ſo in times paſt, and ſo 'tis ſtill. Theſe moaths always gnawing on Learned works. No proſperity ſo circumſpect; that can eſcape the tooth of malice, hatred and envy, always attended the higheſt things. I obſerved, when it was conſulted about the recalling of the Jeſuits into <hi>France,</hi> that two ſorts of men did ſpecially oppoſe themſelves, Hereticks, and looſe living Church-men: The one was moved thereunto by their bad faith, the other by their bad life. But I am ſo far from being hereby moved to alter my intended purpoſe, that I am more confirmed in my reſolution.</p>
                        <p n="17">
                           <hi>17.</hi> The Fathers of the Society, ſpeak and think honourably of the Pope, ſo they ſhould, and ſo do I; I joyn with them, ſince I am certain that in averring and defending the Popes Authority, they differ not from other Catholick Divines.</p>
                        <p n="18">
                           <hi>18.</hi> Neither did their Doctrine ever give occaſion to Clergy-men to deny me Tribute. Now is there any to be found whom theſe Fathers Words or Books animated to Killing of Kings. Whatſoever ſome have patcht together to bring them to diſcredit, is all a Fiction and meer Fable. Thirty years and more are paſſed ſince the Fathers began to inſtruct the Youth of <hi>France</hi> both in Vertue and Learning. Of theſe ſome have gone through with all their ſtudies in their Schools. Others have broke off, and applyed themſelves to Phiſick or Law. Tell me whether any of theſe ever learnt of their Maſters to lay hands upon Kings, and to kill them? I tell you the Fathers are ſo clear, that they are content to appeal even to their enemies judgement. There are ſome Pulpit-men among the Hereticks, who were trained up in the Fathers Schools: Ask theſe men their judgment concerning the Jeſuits Lives and Doctrine: But whoſe cauſe is ſo good as to deſire to be tryed by Enemies? Yet I am ſure in their caſe this has been done, The Miniſters have been asked their judgments of the Jeſuits: And they have given no other anſwer, but, That the Jeſuites Lives cannot be Reprehended, and for their Doctrine, that it is in too clear a Sun for to be queſtioned. Surely few can be found that will dare to ſtand to their Enemies judgment, their ſecurity of Conſcience muſt needs be great, that fears not any Adverſaries Verdict.</p>
                        <p n="19">
                           <hi>19.</hi> The Confeſſion of <hi>Barriere,</hi> who attempted againſt my perſon, doth not infringe that which I have ſaid. For ſo far was any Jeſuit from that fact (which you nevertheleſs affirm) that one of theſe Fathers of good credit adviſed me of it in time, and another of them dehorted and deterred <hi>Barriere</hi> from his Attempt, propoſing to him Goods heavy Judgments due to ſuch Malefactors.</p>
                        <p n="20">
                           <hi>20.</hi> As for <hi>Catel,</hi> all imaginable torments, were not able to wreſt the leaſt word againſt <hi>Varadius</hi> or any one Father of the Society. If this be not ſo, why ſpared you the guilty? Why let you them go when you had them faſt? why puniſhed you them not according to your Laws and Court?</p>
                        <p n="21">
                           <hi>21.</hi> But to grant you that that never was; ſuppoſe ſome one of the Society had attempted againſt my perſon. Will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all the Apoſtles for one <hi>Judas?</hi> ſhall the puniſhment light on my head, for whatſoever any of Souldiers ſhall treſpaſs in Military Licenſe? I acknowledge the hand of God, whoſe will it was to have me preſſed and humbled at that time; the ſame hand raiſed me, and ſet me ſafe again. Gods goodneſs and providence be thanked. I have learnt to forget and forgive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries for Gods ſake, as I willingly do for that King who is greater than my ſelf. And now I will be ſo far from remembring injuries done unto me, or revenging the ſame, that I will dayly offer up prayers for my enemies. All of us have need of Gods mercy, which is no ways better to be obtained, then by promptly and readily pardoning thoſe who have offended <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>NOw it is plain by this Diſcourſe, that this great and wiſe Prince had well conſider'd what he ſpoke of; and had he found their Doctrine to be ſuch as is pretended, he would have been too nearly concern'd to have become their Advocate and Protector.</p>
            <p>As for the pretended horrid Ceremony for Conſecrating a Perſon and Dagger, deſign'd for a Royal Maſſacre. I will only ſpeak of it in the Authors own words; that it is an Invention of Men worſe than Devils, a Lie indeed of ſo impudent a nature, that it is enough to amaze Heaven it ſelf, to ſee how Devils Incarnate can out-do in malice the Spirits of everlaſting Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Let any impartial eye obſerve the Countries our Author ſums up to baniſh the Jeſuits; and beſides that, he will find falſe cauſes aſſigned in moſt, it not all the examples; He does in his laſt overthrow all that he has ſaid, for if <hi>Ferdinando</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was Expelled his Kingdom for endeavouring the Re-admiſſion of the Jeſuits, then it is as plain that he did not believe they held Tenents deſtructive to Kings, as it is that theſe did who deſtroyed him, as much as in them lay by Expelling him his Kingdom for defending the Jeſuits. <hi>Thus malice makes men blind:</hi> But above all, who can believe him, when he ſays Father <hi>Harcourt</hi>'s Letter about Sir <hi>Edmondberry Godfrey</hi>'s Murther written three Hours after it was done is ſo publickly to be ſeen, when any man that reads the Tryal may perceive it could not be produced; and if it were found ſince, and ſo publick as he pretends, no doubt our Author would have as well recited it, as refer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to it, for doing ſo would have been worth all he hath ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99450:3"/>
            <p>As to their Prayers for the Judges and Accuſers, in my Judgment they were more likely to proceed from Charity than Malice, let our good natur'd Author be of another Opinion if he pleaſes, but his reaſon for the contrary is none; for it is well known St. <hi>Stephen</hi> at his Stoning did the ſame, and yet deſired neither Prayers nor Tears of thoſe that were not of his own profeſſion, but it's true thoſe Prayers may become Curſes to the Witneſſes, if the Depoſition againſt them be as falſe, as it is evident ſome of what they have Depoſed to King and Councel hath been, as I could inſtance in the Caſe of <hi>Don John,</hi> and divers other matters, if I were minded to diſparage the Kings Witneſſes, as they call them: But this I cannot forbear obſerving, that it may be juſtly ſaid of ſome of them, as Doctor <hi>Dun</hi> ſays of Witches, <hi>That they confeſs things impoſſible.</hi> But leaving them to the great Judge of all things, I will only remind them of this Truth, that if they betray innocent Blood for Gain, and make Gods Name contemptible, by invoking it to a Falſehood; no Equivocation, nor Mental Reſervation, will ſhelter them from his dreadful vengeance which he in his due time will viſit them with: And it is a thouſand to one he will for Terror to others and Diſpair to themſelves, make them the moſt miſerable and contemptible wretches breathing in this World; but if they have Sworn Truth, let them give a luſter to it by amending their Lives, that they and the Nation they have ſaved by their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries may glory in one another, to the confuſion and deſtruction not only of theſe, but all other its enemies.</p>
            <p>But to conclude, I will deſire but any reaſonable man to conſider the abſurdity of their Arguing, who pretend that not only theſe laſt five, but the eight others condemned by the ſame Evidence, had Diſpenſations to die with Lyes in their Mouths: And that by the Doctrine of Equivocation and Mental Reſervation, they and all other Papiſts can ſay and Swear any thing, when it is plain to all the world, that nothing but their fearing to Swear falſely layes them lyable to the Laws againſt Popery; can it be believed that men who forfeit Peerage, Offices of Honour, Truſt, Power and Profit, looſe two thirds of their Eſtates, and make themſelves more obnoxious to more ſevere Laws than ever was in force againſt Chriſtianity during the firſt ten Perſecutions, and all this becauſe they will not Swear againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, can have Diſpenſations ſo covenient to their earthly well being, and make no uſe of them; nothing can be more contradictory to humain reaſon then theſe Calumnies, nor can any indifferent perſon chuſe but ſee through ſuch abſurd contradictions. In fine there has thirteen men, of which one a Proteſtant, have died already by the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of theſe four Witneſſes, all have gone out of the World abſolutely denying the matters they were accuſed of, any one of them might have ſecured a Pardon by confeſſing his Charge; they have been all of them of approved Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Coverſation in their ſeveral callings during the reſt of their Lives, and yet we muſt not believe one tittle of their laſt words ſpoke ſo plainly, (if falſe) to their deſtruction both here and hereafter; to their deſtruction, and not the leaſt to their Intereſt: Yet on the contrary we are not ſo much as allow'd to doubt the Fidelity of their Accuſers, though men Notorious for Scandalous and Wicked Lives; men who from abject qualities aſſume to themſelves by this means Dignities, and pretend to Honours and Titles; and who from the extreameſt Poverty and Neceſſity are advanced to Opolency and Plenty for Accuſing perſons of Conſulting with them about Affairs of ſo high a nature as the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Kingdoms, and Murthering the beſt of Monarchs. Perſons of ſuch Qualities and Fortunes, as would with <hi>Job</hi> have diſdained to ſet them with the Dogs of their Flock, who if they would have made uſe of ſuch pitiful Inſtruments, would certainly have taken care for their ſupport, and not have ſeconded their Imprudent Election of ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors in matter of ſo great Truſt, with a ſecond Error of ſuffering them to want when they had truſted them, but would have provided for them as thoſe we ſee do ſufficiently, who now make uſe of their ſervice; but though we may not call them perjured perſons until Convicted, which their Protectors will eaſily prevent, by not permitting them to be Indicted, yet none can deny us the libetty of thinking that men will eaſily diſcern the difference between the Dying and the Living Teſtimonies, let their Pretences and Lyes be never ſo many; But to the God of Truth we refer both Cauſes, not doubting but in his good time all theſe ſecrets will be brought to Light to his everlaſting Glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce the former, there is come forth another Paper called, <hi>An Anſwer to the Jeſuits Speeches, by</hi> Eſrael Tong <hi>D. D.</hi> full frought with labour and ſtudied falſehoods, but ſo plainly malicious, that no body who had not been a witneſs of the ſucceſs of their ill ſpun improbable ſtories in their firſt pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſcoveries, could have had the leaſt hope, theſe ſhould have prevailed with one man, ſo contrary to the ſentiments of humain nature. No, we all too well know Sophiſtry vaniſhes at the approach of Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible death, and that Dr. <hi>Tong,</hi> and the more harden'd Impoſture his Companion in Title and Deſign, will find at the approach of that Grim <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher to their Eternal abodes, no reſolution but a good Conſcience can make them follow him Smiling, this Truth writ with an indelable Character in every breast will ſave us a labour to anſwer his frivolous Anatomizing thoſe mens laſt words, delivered ſo cheerfully and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at their Execution; only we may ſafely make reflection on the last Paragraph of his Impious and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Paper, where he ſays, <hi>It is no more then they expected,</hi> a Truth undeniable as to him and his Companions, who cannot but be Conſcious to themſelves whether the Evidence given againſt them be true or falſe, and from that might well expect their denial, which no man elſe that believed them guilty did or could: But it is in vain to warn thinking people from making natural reflections on theſe mens dying words, until it be proved that they made it their practice to violate all Laws Humain and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, by better Evidence then ſuch as have been notoriouſly guilty of doing ſo, by a continued ſeries of Cheating, Stealing, Robberies, Perjury and Burggery, and all other unnatural Crimes and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleaneſſes ſufficiently known, and above denial publick to the whloe World; but what Truth can be expected from a low ſpirited Wretch, who for a little Money (of which he complains he has been Couſened too) can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to debaſe his Character of Divine to be the <hi>Zany</hi> or Deputy Devil to ſuch Mountebanks.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
